I've been coming across a suta um like
few few days or a few days ago. The
question is um is suffering created by
oneself is suffering created by another
is suffering created by both oneself or
another or is suffering created by
neither like just arise randomly. Um so
I was contemplating like the Buddha like
say like it's neither of those basically
yet we often say inside that you are
responsible >> and so I think it would be good to like
>> and so I think it would be good to like
kind of distinguish what's the
difference between being responsible
>> and you are um creator of your suffering
because there is kind of a difference
there but I think it would be good to
>> yeah
what's the difference between being
responsible for your suffering. You're
creating your suffering
because there is that common view um in
in some teachings where where you would
be told that kind of in the moment you
create the suffering
by kind of the way you
direct your attention or something like
that. So
is that is that the same as saying that
you're responsible for your suffering?
Is that what you mean when you say that?
So maybe we should start
clarifying what the suffering is
>> basically. So because I think this is
the most important question.
>> Yeah.
I could say the suffering the root of
the suffering is untained mind.
>> Right? That's the root of the suffering.
What is the suffering itself?
not seeing the mind
that is untamed it's basically
>> yeah the same as that that's still the
root or the the cause of the suffering
like you would say ignorance is a is a
cause of suffering but the suffering
itself let's say like phenomenologically
without looking at something else you
just experience suffering right Now
let's say just what is that suffering
without overthinking it?
>> It's unpleasant.
>> Yeah, it's it's just unpleasant feeling.
So yes, you you can think about why the
suffering is there and that's pretty
much what we're going to go into. But
first of all, it's important to be clear
that yeah, that's what suffering is. Is
just experiencing unpleasant
unpleasantness. >> But wait, is that the origin of the
>> But wait, is that the origin of the
suffering?
>> Is that the origin of the suffering?
>> No, no, no, no. That's what we said.
We're going to get into what the origin
of the suffering suffering is, but now
we're just saying suffering in of
itself. What? What is it?
>> Mhm.
>> Duka
>> just ded
feeling unpleasant feeling. Okay.
>> So, um,
so that's what it is. So, so that's what
we're talking about. It's not some, uh,
because people can get into kind of
metaphysical almost like
>> um, proliferations about suffering being
this and being that, but really it's
just right here and now you feel an
unpleasant um feeling. There's some kind of
um feeling. There's some kind of
dissonance, conflict, dissatisfaction.
um unhappiness,
>> resistance.
>> Well,
>> that would be what's causing the
suffering, but the suffering itself is
just Yeah.
>> So,
so that's what the suffering is. Now,
let's say you're experiencing a
unpleasant feeling
on account of whatever.
Can you get rid of it immediately? So So
can you
even kind of
be sure that things that you will do
will result in that feeling going away
as at any point?
>> No, don't be sure.
>> Yeah. So you can hope that um you know
traveling the world
uh and attaining all the riches in the
world and getting all you want even if
you actually get what you wanted you can
hope that that will result in changing
the feeling that has arisen but it may
well not happen. And that's the root of
all problems in the world. It's that you
have a feeling and you can't change it.
So
from that point of view it becomes quite
clear that saying that you are the
creator of your suffering would not be
quite accurate because if you were you
would be able to
um decide and for that matter actually
if you have tamed your mind if you have
undone these origins of suffering that
we're going to get into
um then even if you said I want to
suffer. I I try to suffer
then you wouldn't be able to which also
adds to the point that no it's not your
creation cuz otherwise it would be fully
under your will.
So now um
>> yeah and it wouldn't be a problem in the
first place.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Because then you could
decide like actually people kind of say
that sometimes like they say um
suffering is a necessary part of life
because it helps you grow. Um, which
isn't completely wrong. Like it's not
like you're trying to to be kind of in
happy la land all the time, but some
there will be difficulties regardless of
what you do in life. But um saying that
that um pretending like it's it's
like it's not a problem, like it's fine
kind of implies that still that ignorant
view that you fundamentally have control
over it. you don't you don't really
realize that you're pretty much confined
uh within it and that like most of the
time the things you do work in changing
it but if you just
contemplate like that's why the Buddha
encourage people every day contemplates
I am liable to sickness I am liable to
aging I am liable to death because those
are the things where an unpleasant
feeling will arise and no matter what
you do you won't be able to get rid of
it. So
um unless your mind is tainted. So
um
then you recognize Yeah. So it is a
problem. It is a it is something that
that um I can't kind of cover it up because
um I can't kind of cover it up because
factually all of all of my issues, all
of my concerns revolve around unpleasant
feeling. So now So now
um
having established that what does it
mean to say that because see you could
it could sound now as as if okay so it's
just you're subjected to it you were
you're kind of a victim of feeling
and I think that would almost sound as
if it's randomly arisen like it just
comes on its own
>> or as or it just imposed on you by
somebody else by by God or or by
something that you have no control over.
So, but we're saying that's not the
case. Um, so what does it mean then to
say that you're responsible practically?
practically?
How how how would you
know that okay I'm responsible for this
feeling that has arisen if it's not like
a momentary thing that I'm just like
kind of um like we said creating it in
that immediate sense
what would it be
Well, there seems to be a like on a
practical level, there are things that I
there's a
there are choices that I can make that
seem to reduce myself.
>> So, it seems that I I do have a an
influence.
But is it a direct answer?
Um
>> can't say for sure.
>> Yeah. So it depends.
>> Yeah. Um like um
direct influence would be if you have
train trained your mind as we were
saying >> but uh
>> but uh
before that practically speaking yeah
what you what your um
>> well let me not give the answer. So, so
let's say what would lead
>> to the arising of an unpleasant feeling
not not how you could get rid of it
>> but like just how did it come about in
the first place.
>> So it's because one delight in what's
pleasant then when this pleasure
disappear >> it kind of
>> it kind of
like this dependency on pleasure like is
>> felt unpleasantly because now the
>> pleasure is not available anymore.
>> Yeah. So, so basically is it correct to
say that the unpleasant feeling is just
the unpleasant circumstance?
>> No, it's more like the kind of what I
build up in regard to it. What what kind
of
um
because I'm so dependent on pleasure
when this pleasure disappear I feel like
what's left quote unquote as
displeasure. But that depends on how
much on my dependency and pleasure not
about the circumstance itself.
>> Yeah. So, so in other words, you can
have unpleasant circumstances
which are
Yeah. Like I said, sickness, aging and
death. Um but whether there's an
unpleasant feeling
felt on account of that like
dissatisfaction or that acute level of
the mind being unhappy
that depends not on the situation
depends on what you have cultivated
where your mind is. Um, so there are
certain actions that you would do that
would make you be hit or struck
by the arrow of pain when unpleasant
circumstances arise which inevitably is
going to happen. So that's why the
Buddha said I think in one suts
that are suitable for the arising of
unpleasant feeling. And so when there is
the kind of um suitable basis, he kind
of gave the simile of like um
like a like two blocks of wood coming
together or something like that that
they make a noise. It's like
uh when the suitable conditions are
there, this unpleasant contact will will
arouse an unpleasant feeling.
So it's not talking about some kind of
external um relationship of the biochemistry kind
um relationship of the biochemistry kind
of thing. No, it's it's that internal
like you said um
situation or or internal
um how could you put it climate of your
own mind that you've built up based on
your actions. that's going to determine
whether unpleasant feeling arise in the
first place. If you were to
actually cultivate actions that don't
that are not suitable for the arising of
suffering um even things that aroused displeasure
um even things that aroused displeasure
before would uh not either not perturb
the mind or even lead to the happiness
of renunciation as the sut would
describe like when the mind develops
Janna then rough rough roads rough food
or no food um uh living in under under a
tree and and just not little to no
medicine would would feel factually like
heavenly requisites.
So you realize it's the exact same thing
that would have before
given rise to displeasure because of the
choices the right choices that you've
been cultivating choices that were not
suitable for the accumulation of craving
actually deacum
or diminish your craving. Now uh you
there is no arising of suffering. So
you can directly see then so that's what
it means to say that you're responsible.
It's it's it's not about um
of course it matters what you do in the
moment because in the moment that's
that's that's where your direct input is
but the arising of suffering is
determined by what you what you've
cultivated. Um Um
so
from that point of view then you realize
because as the Buddha said cra okay so
craving is the root of suffering but
but
does that mean that you can
the same question that I asked before
does that mean that you can just I've
been doing whatever I want not paying
attention to my actions but I have the
direct insight of what craving is so I
just Cut it off at the last moment. >> No,
>> No,
>> that's not possible.
>> No.
>> So because see it's not you like yes you
can on top of the mind having craving
you can also act out of craving which
means you're making it worse.
>> But fundamentally what what the Buddha
means when he says craving is a root of
suffering. It means a mind affected with
craving is the root of suffering. Like
the the wild animal as we were
describing it in those a few discussions
ago maybe
>> uh it's it's
whether you like it or not. Basically
experiencing certain situations with
that type of mind will mean suffering is
there. >> Yeah. There's a bit of a delay between
>> Yeah. There's a bit of a delay between
you on the on the one hand and minds. So
minds can be calm but if you then start
behaving inappropriately
>> you will stir it up but that's not
immediately noticeable.
>> Yeah.
>> But at some point you will notice and
then you can calm down but it will take
then time again for the mind to calm
down. >> And how do you calm down?
>> And how do you calm down?
>> Well,
>> it's by first of all you have to stop
doing the things that led you to that.
Yeah. You don't calm down by kind of um
putting out I I I grab a perfect fire
extinguisher, but I continue to throw
wood on the fire.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> so then the responsibility, which was
the original question, the
responsibility is on what you do, but
depending on let's say how pliable the
mind is or on how how well it has been
tamed and hence listens to you, there
will be somewhat of a delay. But when
you go in the wrong direction and you
agitate that mind, then you will suffer
on account of it.
>> So if you make if you keep that
distinction between you and mind, you
can see how there can be responsibility
and how that is not in conflict with a
mind that suffers. Mhm.
>> So the whole point is of course to tame
the mind in such a way that it cannot
become agitated again on account of you
first of all being restrained and then
the mind understanding that it is better
off if it is tamed and trained and then
it doesn't want to go back anymore.
>> Yeah.
>> That that will be the let's say final
result of all this.
>> Yeah. And and uh that brings us to one
point that I was thinking about bringing
up, but actually this is a good good
context to to do it to do it in. Um
because sometimes
um there's this idea that you should
kind of that if you let's say try to
incline towards seclusion and you don't
really interact with people and you
don't really go out into the world then
you're just running away and you you're
not really kind of developing yourself.
So you actually have to expose yourself
to the temptations in order to build up
your ability to kind of not be moved by
them, let's say.
So in light of what we've been
discussing now, what's wrong with what's
wrong with that? Yeah,
>> that is true for an art, but for someone
that is already affected by craving um
the circumstance do matter because
otherwise you will just expose himself
to things that agitate the mind
regardless of what you think on top of
it. >> Yeah. Yeah. So that do that's one angle
>> Yeah. Yeah. So that do that's one angle
you can look at it. It's like well it's
not about what I it's not about whether
I'm able to not act out. um it's about
what am I inclining the mind towards
simply by putting myself in this
environment but more acutely
uh
what what is the
why why is it wrong basically what like
>> why is it why is seclusion the ideal and
not >> um
>> um
why specifically seclusion
>> well something that comes to mind is
It's not like the mind will suddenly uh
be tamed by or like the problem that the
problem of an untamed mind will
disappear into
>> anything will be more revealed.
>> Y
>> um
>> so like you would still have to
well learn how to train it.
>> Y
>> inclusion and probably have a better
perspective on that training.
>> Yeah.
>> Than you would
>> Mhm. when you're
still in contact with many of the things
that you're
which led to it.
>> But what would be the training that you
would do in seclusion that you cannot do
>> when you're just in front of the
temptations >> cuz that's true. It will reveal the the
>> cuz that's true. It will reveal the the
training you have to do. But but what is
>> the training and why can it only be done
in seclusion? I think first we should
clarify what seclusion is
>> because seclusion is not that at the
beginning you can just go to solitude
and say that you practice seclusion
say that you practice seclusion
>> because seclusion is a particular
step in the gradual training.
>> Mhm. So
>> yeah, of course. So So that has to be
>> very developed.
>> Yeah.
>> Already
to to go to the seclusion
>> that that has to be kind of covered like
um you you don't jump into seclusion
when you're still not able to keep the
precepts. >> But let's say somebody did establish
>> But let's say somebody did establish
themselves in the precepts did um become
proficient in sense restraint. But now
they start to feel like okay so but see
if I now go into seclusion I'm actually
not developing myself. I have to go out
to test myself
>> that I'm actually able to keep the
precepts in in every situation. Yeah.
>> So in that scenario,
um why is it that actually the seclusion
is what would allow them
>> to tame their minds properly in light of
what we've been saying that it's the
suffering that you're responsible for
>> based on your actions.
>> Yeah. Well, you see the thing is this in
seclusion what comes with the seclusion
is that there's basically nothing to do.
>> Mhm. So that means that when you are
doing things, you are now in a position
to see whether it is that untamed mind
pushing you to do it or not because
there's basically nothing else there but
you and your mind. If you are not in
seclusion and there's other people and
hence interaction or things to be done
in the world including resisting the
temptations that you want to test
yourself against, you are not now going
to see what is motivating you to do
something. if that's coming from that
mind pressuring you or random
circumstances that you are reacting to.
>> That's all the difference there.
>> Yeah. So, but like let's say
specifically in regards to the precepts,
>> let's say let's say I'm training myself
to not never break the precepts.
>> So, if I think I need to go out there
>> and experience this pressure to break
the precepts
>> to make sure that I don't break it.
>> Yeah. But that is already a lopsided
view on what the whole purpose of the
precepts are.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But why why is it why is it
that's only in seclusion
>> seclusion would make you unable to break
the precepts not going out into the
world. >> Mhm. Well, because as I said earlier
>> Mhm. Well, because as I said earlier
then you will see because as you said in
earlier talks the whole point of these
precepts is precisely to show you what
your mind is up to.
>> Mhm.
>> And that is what you're going to see in
seclusion. >> Exactly. So in relation to the precepts
>> Exactly. So in relation to the precepts
specifically what what will happen in
regard to the mind? Well, you see, if if
somebody has some basic training in
keeping the precepts externally, what
you will now practically discover is
that there is a lot of room in between
those precepts where where you are clear
I'm not breaking these precepts. But if
you have understood that those precepts
are not just there in order to not be
broken, but to basically turn your
attention around in order to see what
the actual intentions are, that is now
what you're going to see in solution. So
that you can refine that same principle
and basically pick up those hints and
signs of the mind because that's the
level where the purification happens. So
the whole direction of your
investigation is in that opposite
direction of worldly temptations which
will always be there.
>> Yeah. So but what so what what would be
the signs of the what signs of what
would you be picking up?
>> Well of the mind.
>> Yeah. The mind but the mind doing what?
Well, the mind basically re resisting
that space where nothing needs to happen
for example. So which will manifest ines
or boredom or loneliness or doubt or
basically all of that which is which
you're going to just overlook if there
are other people or or the strange idea
that you
>> that you need to go out and
>> this whole notion that you want to test
not breaking the precepts is itself
already your mind pushing you from a
very strange angle. So, so you want to
not even go down that road. But just
assuming that, right? Because that was
the question.
>> So even but even more specifically is
like what would your mind be doing in
seclusion? Let's say you just got used
to keeping the precepts externally. You
don't really break them. What would the
mind be doing and screaming?
>> Yeah. But to to what?
>> To you putting pressure on you to start
doing things.
>> Yes. But to start doing what?
>> To get rid of unpleasantly.
What will the mind be? Let's let's give
a hint. What will the mind be thinking
about? Somebody who just established the
precepts. >> Sexuality, aversion.
>> Sexuality, aversion.
>> Well, it would Yeah. So, it will be
thinking about breaking the precepts.
So, in other words,
>> right? I see. When you go into when you
just establish yourself
>> externally,
unless you're distracting yourself with
other stuff, if you're actually in
seclusion, um with some degree of space to be aware
um with some degree of space to be aware
of your own mind, as you were saying,
what you will practically find, not
always, but sometimes, what you will
find is that the mind will incline
towards those very thoughts that are in
line with what you externally don't uh
they're at against with what you now
externally don't do. So yeah, thoughts
of sensuality, thoughts of um the things
that you have abandoned
and see based on what you do there in
see based on what you do there in
seclusion
>> that will you will be responsible for
the pressure, the dissatisfaction, the
the the pain that will come up when you
go out there in the world and encounter
things. If if in seclusion you have
developed yourself properly and you have
not been welcoming thoughts of breaking
the precepts, thoughts that kind of push
you in that direction, then when you go
out, your mind will not be experiencing
the temptation in the first place. There
will not be pain on account of not doing
those things. So when you go out into
the world and you experience kind of um
pressure and and and
um to to do those things specifically to
break the precepts, you might experience
you know random agitations and other
things because the mind is untamed. But
if you were specifically feeling
pressure in that direction, it's because
mentally you haven't fully
>> de
>> pulled pulled the mind back. And
sometimes you still
>> when the mind kind of wants to think
about it, you still
>> kind of allow it
>> to to at least mentally welcome that
direction. So, so when you when you
basically do that like that practice
where you go out and expose yourself to
temptations, what you're really doing is
training your willpower
and willpower has nothing to do with um
like taming the mind. It's even I think
the the scientist or neurologist or
something recognized that willpower is a
limited resource. It's like if if you've
been if you spend all your willpower in
a very hard thing in the morning, uh
then by the evening you're much more
likely to just kind of
>> fall asleep,
>> give in and and or or yeah or any kind
of just go for the loweffort
um alternative in everything that comes
up. >> So you don't want to be relying on
>> So you don't want to be relying on
willpower and training your willpower.
It's it's like it's it's uh dependent on
very impermanent conditions like
motivation, inspiration and that's not
what the tamed mind is actually what
actually is.
>> Tamed mind is I don't experience desire
to do this in the first place. Mhm.
>> So that's why then in seclusion if you
take responsibility
even for these mental actions like never
on on any occasion for no reason do you
allow yourself to welcome thoughts of
breaking the precepts like the lighting
in it even if I'm not spe specifically
planning to do it
then you won't you won't experience that
that like that pain will not come about
that duka will not come about on account
of not breaking those precepts and
that's how you become established if
because you can spend the whole life
um externally not doing those things but
that's like just take a child
uh who who kind of didn't go through
puberty or something and just lived his
whole life like that he would probably
find it pretty easy not to break the
precess but does that mean that he is
actually developed
>> in that's that simile of the the the new
newborn child that the Buddh gave it's
like if if just on account of not doing
these things you were to be considered a
sum then a baby is like a newborn baby
is like the foremost summoner because
he's like not even
>> doesn't even have the doesn't even know
what those things are
>> doesn't have thoughts of sensuality
doesn't even know other
So, so how can it be angry if it doesn't
understand what other beings are and so
on. >> So it's not just about so your point
>> So it's not just about so your point
this is not just about keeping the
precepts externally and not breaking
them. >> It's about devaluing that direction
>> It's about devaluing that direction
>> internally on the level of whether you
allow the light
the light
>> to occur towards those things. And that
delight you can only see it as you were saying
you can only see it as you were saying
like seeing those signs recognizing
those inclinations of the mind
>> that only becomes apparent in seclusion.
>> Yeah.
>> So so quite contrary well the problem
often is like when people go into
seclusion they would think it's just
about kind of going on vacation from the
problems and just forgetting about
everything which kind of ties in with
the whole view of of what people think
meditation is. But no, it's like if you
if you go in seclusion properly,
um practically speaking, unless you're
in Janna, that that's what's going to be
happening. Like your mind is going to be
throwing these baits at you
>> and uh you will have to to be on guard
because you could easily um take one of
them and that's how you're keeping your
keeping that connection.
>> Yeah. And here we can also make a
further distinction between bodily and
mental seclusion. So bodily seclusion is
to not have other people around and to
just be on your own for most of the day,
nobody to talk to and so on. But then if
you still on the mental level welcome
let's say thoughts of sensuality or um
uh or other things then then you are
bodily secuded but mentally you're not
secluded. >> Yeah. The Buddha said you have a
>> Yeah. The Buddha said you have a
companion if you have craving.
>> Yeah. Companion quotes. Well exactly
companion quote unquote. So um so when
that craving is seen as uh is recognized
uh more precisely as welcoming and
delighting in those thoughts or
alternatively resisting them wanting to
get rid of them so you so you don't do
either uh and so then you don't have
craving as a companion that would be the
mental seclusion
>> but that mental seclusion because that's
that's now another view which I have
actually heard that that people say yeah
well the highest one is the mental
seclusion so let's just go and sit in
the morning and evening pes together and
develop mental seclusion. Well, but
that's not now how it works. So, you
first have to be quite okay with
yourself in the bodily seclusion and
then recognize that that is a stepping
stone to train your mind to become
mentally secluded from an awesome
states. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, that's how how always the
sutas would describe it. It's like yes
they would sometimes mention okay
there's the higher mental seclusion but
when it comes to the training you would
always describe first a monk seeks out
physical seclusion on the basis of which
he develops mental seclusion.
>> Yeah.
>> Um so so
>> there's also that s in
um which talks about being developed in
body developed in mind. Is that along
the same lines in terms of feeling?
>> What are we feeling? Being developed in
>> Yeah. 37 or something.
>> Yeah. Yeah. 36.
>> 36.
>> It says like uh
>> Yeah. So that um you're developed in
body when when pleasure arises the mind
is not occupied.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And not taken by that pleasure.
And you're developed in mind when uh
when pain arises. The mind is not
occupied by pain and and suffering. But
see the the critical thing to recognize
there is like experientially speaking if
the mind is not taken by it, if the mind
is not preoccupied by it,
practically speaking it's not suffering.
So it's just like a unpleasant
circumstance like I said before. So
suffering is not determined by the
external condition. It determined by
whether internally there is that
um dissonance or or sense of um
that you're that you're basically losing
something. And of course the only way
that that's going to be there is if
there's craving. If you needed or or
desired to be otherwise, then that's the
automatic pain is the automatic result.
So, but again, it's it's it's that mind
that that's put into that state of
craving or taken away from it by the
things that you do. It's not like a
choice of just okay, I'll just be
economist and be okay with the moment.
Well, you needed to be aimous
yesterday and the day before and seven
days ago when you were engaging in unh
wholesome things. That's when you had to
be a quandomous not at the last moment.
>> Yeah. You have to be economist by not
engaging those unh wholesome things.
>> Exactly. Yeah. So um
so yeah otherwise you're just practicing
like damage control like just okay the
house is house is on fire and success is
putting out the fire not preventing the
house from getting burnt in the first
place. So now
um
having said all that
what do you do now let's say you because
you you you
like obviously there's a limit to that
like you will be not engaging uh you
will be pure in your conduct at least as
far as you can see
and uh sometimes
dissatisfaction will still arise like
you will reflect and you will see okay
have I done something wrong? Have I
broken any precepts? Have I delighted in
unh wholesome things? And uh as far as
you can see, you haven't. And yet still
the mind is going to be experiencing
Luka, which
which
okay, does that mean that it randomly
arose now? No. Uh of course, from a
theoretical point of view, yes, that
duka wouldn't have arisen if you were
fully developed. So you're responsible
for it.
But um there is a way out there. There
is a way that you could develop yourself
without um
giving up responsibility for the fact
that well that suffering shouldn't be
there in the first place without falling
into management. In other words,
you could at least
um reestablish yourself in a way that
you will wear away
the conditions for that suffering to be
there. So what would be that that thing
that you can do? If your conduct is not
in check, then you you need to look at
that first because otherwise um again
you you can't
um
throw water in a raging fire. You have
to you have to just not not have it be
there. But
now let's say that's covered.
What can you do to to let's say rectify
the situation?
So the situation is just just to recap
like your conduct your precept as far as
we can see is okay but you still somehow
suffer for some
>> yeah you're in seclusion and
>> suffer
>> you're not doing anything bad you're not
uh thinking in your wholesome thoughts
but still there's that kind of
uneasiness and sense of something's
wrong. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> Nothing specific just kind of work to
do. >> Yeah.
see the pressure of something wrong.
>> Mhm. And and
>> uh but but but what's the
what would that be like? Cuz
if you just look at the pressure, that
could be interpreted in different ways.
But how could how would you explain it
in the most accurate way?
Being aware of the pressure it's felt.
>> Mhm. It's not some acute painful
feeling, but it's like more like
uneasiness. >> Um even without anything particular
>> Um even without anything particular
happening.
>> Mhm. And uh
but is that it? Did do you see that
pressure or is there something else that
you shouldn't lose sight of not distracting
not distracting
myself from that uneasiness?
>> Mhm.
>> Not searching for any even even
slightest seemingly
even not unh wholesome
activity. M
I think what kind of need to be
recognized there is that peace come from
like recognizing things as they are and
not engaging with them.
>> Recognizing like this relationship with
whatever right
>> not in trying to change the things and
that's the difficulty is to
>> stay with what's there and while this
difficulty is happening finding that
peace actually come from not interfering
inter with it. So can you just choose
not to to not interfere?
>> Can not choose
>> or is there a specific way
that you that you that you become unable
to interfere with things even if you
want to interfere with them?
Is there something that you have to see
or do you just decide not to interfere?
>> As I said, just see this pressure as a
whole. Yes, that's
>> But how do you see the pressure?
>> Well, okay. No, you see the pressure,
but is that the whole picture? Is that
all there is?
>> Yeah. No, no. So, so this is what I'm
asking. So that so there's so you can
say just see the pressure, but there are
other ways in in in which you can see
the pressure. So
>> yeah, because see if you have if you
only see the pressure, then you can
I hope I'm not giving way too much too
much hints now. Um if you only see the
pressure uh you could basically become
overly kind of you could actually
practically speaking you could lose
perspective over your experience because
see that now becomes like a particular
>> thing that you're concerned about and
and even though initially maybe you
recognize the pressure
>> you can still
>> so you can recognize the pressure but
with the intention of trying to get rid
of
>> Yeah. Exactly. you don't recognize still
it's rooted me watching the pressure and
looking at it and and contemplating it
is rooted in trying to get rid of it. So
>> how do you keep the pressure where it
is? >> Uhhuh.
>> Uhhuh.
>> And without interfering with it.
>> Mhm. Yeah. Yeah.
>> That's the sound.
>> There is something more specific still
which nobody has yet said.
>> We did actually discuss it already. I
think in a previous talk
if we're talking about the same thing.
>> Well, um I'm not going to give too many
hints but uh I think
>> yeah okay so um look um if that pressure
is owned and that mind is seen as yours
then you will not have the right
perspective on it.
>> Yes. And how do you discern things?
>> No but that's first is that that is the
way that it should should be regarded.
So yeah. So then how do you teach tone
on things? That's not the next question.
>> Yeah,
>> because I mean once you have understood
it like what disowning is yeah you can
just directly okay I I disown this
>> but uh that's not how you start. So
there's a
>> yeah so so how you start is by
recognizing that anything that you know
want to do
>> about that pressure
that that can only happen when you have
already owned the pressure and regard it
as yours.
>> So you basically have to endure that
pressure which will eventually if you do
it rightly in the context that we have
sketched will result in the insight that
wait there's that pressure it's real as
such as we often say but it's now not
yours. Yeah.
>> And that will and at some point that
distinction between
mind which is pressuring you and you
that will become fully clear. What then
happens with what we now call you. Okay.
That can now be a next topic but but you
but that line becomes very clear and
then also that will also practically now
answer the question of where is your
responsibility and where it isn't. So
you will no longer be over or under
shooting. In other words, you understand
now a little bit.
>> Yeah. All that's quite correct but but
there's a specific way that you endure
things because again like if you if you
have grasped the signs of what enduring
means then yeah you can just say I'll
endure this
>> and you're rightly enduring it
>> but
>> um
without that perspective being fully
established there's a specific way for
you to
endure things properly. It's still I
guess the the way of there's a specific
way is kind of um okay so I can do
something to deal with this.
>> Well in a way if you understand it
rightly yeah it is the thing that you
have to do but then you realize it's not
really a doing.
>> Yeah.
>> Well yeah at the same time if there's
this unpleasantness
or what can I do?
Is it something you can recognize
without losing sight of or yeah have I
recognized it?
>> Can I try another direction?
>> So okay there is this pressure there and
I can experience this pressure only
because the body is sitting there right
now and I by including these two kind of
>> things which are like two different
perspective on the same aspect of the
experience. Well, then it's quite clear
that me quote unquote that I put in
between in order to make the link in
between of these two is just because I
keep overlooking that there is these
two. >> Yeah. So what what are you doing when
>> Yeah. So what what are you doing when
you what are you contemplating when you
recognize that?
>> Well that even if I would have gave it a
very very specific name.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I know. But like even even
if I want to like own one of them, one
depend on the other. So it's kind of
obvious. I mean when you recognize that
it's kind of obvious that
>> even if you want you cannot do anything.
>> So see that's what that what I that
that's what I was aiming at when you
brought up like yeah you can recognize
the pressure in and of itself but
there's a reason why the Buddha wasn't
saying just just look at one thing. Um
there's a reason why he talked about
recognizing the relationship the
simultaneous relationship between two
things. I never finish my sentence. So
yes, I was trying to say that at the
moment simultaneously
with seeing the pressure that very
uneasiness of the pressure
simultaneously becoming pleasant
basically. So
uh yeah was trying to tell just that.
>> Yeah. Uh you can that can be a way to
look at it like sure you can contemplate
um pressure and and feeling but um
practically speaking
um I think for most people the what you
just said now would be more kind of
palpable like okay regardless of the
pressure I'm experiencing can I see
something that isn't let's say directly
related to that pressure because if you
kind of boil it down okay just that
pressure to try to recognize the
different aspects of it. Um you might
easily just
>> make it an object again and it's just
the loss of the perspective.
>> Exactly. So so if you keep it on that
level like okay what what is I'm
experiencing this pressure
but uh what else is there that that
would prevent me from becoming fully
engaged with the pressure if as long as
I don't as long as as long as I don't lo
lose sight of it. And it's you can say
it's the body. You can say it's just the
overall situation that you're in. Like
sometimes the sutas would even talk
about like the perception of the forest
and would say that if a monk develops
perception of the forest um or
perception of the great earth his mind
will become established in samadi. So
like literally just if you don't forget
that okay I'm in this room right now.
>> You don't make it you don't try to like
psychize and and spec make it any more
specific than that. It's just a general
recognition. Okay, this is where I am
right now. You're not trying to feel
your knees and and you're you're um kind
of touching the floor or or the
sensations of coldness or heat. You just
just a general recognition. I'm in this
room. And then as long as you don't
don't lose sight of that, you won't
become fully identified for the lack of
a better word. Like you won't fully
descend into that pressure. You will be
it will still be pressuring you. it will
still be baiting you but you will have
basically something to hold on to that
like okay I know that as long as I I
don't need to um define or or worry
about like what is the escape from this
pressure and how do I get rid of it all
I need to be concerned about is I just
don't forget these fundamental elements
of my experience that remain unchanged
regardless of what this pressure is
doing because it is going to be we say
pressure as if it's a a static thing.
But practically speaking, it's the mind
thinking about this and that and of
course revolving. Well, for that matter,
you could take the the mood or the the
pressure of the mind as as your
background. You see that as a general
phenomenon. Okay, this is the state that
the mind is in. And then whatever
thoughts about this or that happen to
come up because that's what defines the
pressure. It's it's all these movements
and and worries and concerns. Then you
don't get absorbed in those worries and
concerns because you know okay this all
of this is happening within this mind of
doubt or anger whatever it might be. And
uh and that's what you do practically
speaking when all of your precepts and
all of your conduct and and all of your
behavior is in check and yet still there
is suffering because it will be like
it's that's why it's a gradual training.
It's not that okay I just establish my
conduct and I'm narrow.
um that but see that's exactly why it
comes at that point because now it's
like okay like like there is no wood
that I'm throwing on this fire as long
as I'm as far as I'm aware. So now I'm
in a position to actually
um extinguish it in the proper way that
won't be just kind of
trying to cope with the damage that I
myself created. And um
um now then you realize
it will lead to a very different kind of
result because now you will be if you
develop this principle rightly you will
be even more disincined
to break the precepts to do anything
rooted in greed and delusion because all
of those things are precisely based on
losing this perspective. losing this
perspective of basically the the force
of the background phenomena of your
experience. Greater aversion and delusion is that
Greater aversion and delusion is that
absorption into concerns
and and not recognizing the whole
picture. And um the reason why I brought
that up partly is because
uh I'm pretty sure people wouldn't
realize why that suta talks about
why that suta talks about
uh at the end. Um and in fact I've seen
people who who who talk about
as precisely justifying the view that
you create your suffer that it's like
the kama that you create in the moment
through your attention and then is like
a cycle of like or or like a sequence of
mental events that follow because of
your direct kind of action. Um and the
suta is literally saying no it's not
that you're the creator of your
suffering. >> So uh and so the the when the Buddha
>> So uh and so the the when the Buddha
says this is kind of the the the view or
the the outlook
through which you transcend all of these
four wrong um ways of looking at it.
Like if you don't see that, you're still
liable to assume that you are directly
responsible for it, that you can't get
rid of it, or that it's because of
somebody, something somebody else did to
you that you're suffering, or that it's
just happening because I ate this food
today, so it's kind of randomly arisen.
Unless you see that direct escape quote
unquote of um the noble method as the Buddha
of um the noble method as the Buddha
called it um dependent origination
then um
that's why you will still be subject to
those wrong views. Yeah, I think it's
also worth mentioning because like kind
of reading the suta it's kind of like I
mean like easy to say oh yeah of course
of course like yeah I'm not creating the
suffering it's not random it's not
others it's not both but as you just say
like as long as someone is still subject
to suffering to that extent he doesn't
he doesn't see this principle and you
fall into one of this category
>> so I think it's like the suta is not so
much like trying to give you like the
perfect answer but actually encouraged
to contemplate if you are still
suffering it's because you fall into one
of these four categories.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Because well, if you still
feel angry
>> when anything happens to you on account
of anybody, it's because fundamentally
you still to some extent assume that the
suffering arose because of them.
>> Yeah.
>> When you feel helpless and frustrated
and and angry with yourself, it's
because you think that you created your
suffering. When you feel helpless as
well, it's also because you think that
that's uh it's randomly arisen at the
very least.
>> Huh?
>> Or anxiety. It's like
>> Yeah. Yeah. Anxiety like you think that
kind of something will kind of happen on
its own that will that will um just just
uproot all of my my um composure and and
things will just go downhill
all completely overlooking. No, it's
like if there is no ignorance
as the
thing says suffering cannot arise.
Um even if you want it to arise, even if
other people do bad things to you, even
if random events happen, suffering
cannot arise if you don't have ignorance
of
Another point I wanted to mention also
you mentioned um willpower at some
point. >> Mhm. Um
>> Mhm. Um
and uh I think it's um how do you say
kind of good to make the distinction
like in the line of everything that's
been said what's the difference between
actually will power and develop like
limitless energy as the sometimes say
limitless energy arising
>> and I think it's a there is quite quite
a distinction there also.
>> Yeah. Well, well, that's a good point
because willpower, as we just said, even
scientists recognize willpower is not
limitless. So, that brings it back to the whole
So, that brings it back to the whole
point that we mentioned that it's all of
the wholesome qualities and the unh
wholesome ones as well. Um, they they
have the root in the mind in the chitta,
not in what you intentionally do in this
moment. So it's what you've been inclining the
So it's what you've been inclining the
mind towards that becomes the the that
becomes all of the awakening factors all
of the faculties all of the the the
things that basically like that's why uh
noble disciples for example it's like
they cannot do certain things they
cannot um completely forget the dhamma they
um completely forget the dhamma they
cannot kill they can kill nar kill their
the father. They cannot lose their
context, the perspective that they have
developed because it's not about them
kind of
being so on the ball and perfectly
um attentive all the time. It's about
just the mind having been established
like a certain um basis, certain
framework that you built up and then
regardless of what you do, nothing can
take that away because it's become fully
ingrained and and settled in. So like uh
same free from sensuality.
It's not because like he's constantly
uh thinking about oh this is dangerous,
this is dangerous, I shouldn't engage
with this. Well, that's not freedom.
It's it's it's like even if you
completely relax and throw your hands up
in the air and just kick your legs up
and drink tea or whatever um and and
just don't think about the dharma ever.
The mind doesn't have those inclinations
because it's been developed beforehand
in that way. So then you realize
limitless effort or limit limitless
energy to not engage in these things
because the place from which the
pressure actually came from the mind has
no interest in those things anymore. So
the effort is basically effortless. It's
like I I don't need to keep telling it like
I I don't need to keep telling it like
oh don't do that don't do that like I
did like I did before. it just
established in the the opposite of that.
So it's like I don't need to touch it
basically. And then that's truly
limitless energy and you realize cuz you
see it for yourself the benefit like so
it's a it's a it's a feedback loop
feedback loop. It's like
you teach your own mind. Okay look like
you're not inclining towards this now.
Do you realize how much better this is
compared to everything that it was
before? And once it fully understands
that then even the energy is is like um
not even limitless is like
why do I need energy for it? That's when
the when the Buddhist said like you
complete the work nothing further needs
to be done.